<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>javascript on Sebastian Aigner</title><link>https://sebi.io/tags/javascript/</link><description>Recent content in javascript on Sebastian Aigner</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sebi.io/tags/javascript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Migrating our Kotlin/JS app to the new IR compiler</title><link>https://sebi.io/posts/2021-03-09-migrating-our-kotlinjs-app-to-the-new-ir-compiler/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sebi.io/posts/2021-03-09-migrating-our-kotlinjs-app-to-the-new-ir-compiler/</guid><description>Together with some colleagues, I maintain a small full-stack web application called CodeQuiz, which we built during a 48-hour hackathon at JetBrains, and use at events to gamify learning about Kotlin. I recently migrated its frontend which you can see below (and which is using the kotlin-react wrappers) to the new Kotlin/JS IR compiler backend.
The new compiler made a bunch of issues in our code visible, so I wanted to share my experience of migrating a Kotlin/JS app, and provide some hints on where to look when your app behaves unexpectedly after moving to the IR compiler.</description></item><item><title>Hosting Kotlin/JS on GitHub Pages via GitHub Actions</title><link>https://sebi.io/posts/2021-02-05-hosting-kotlin-js-on-github-pages/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 19:33:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sebi.io/posts/2021-02-05-hosting-kotlin-js-on-github-pages/</guid><description>GitHub Pages is an easy way to host your Kotlin/JS application - and in combination with the continuous integration service GitHub Actions, you can easily set up a smooth development (and deployment!) experience for your projects. Read on to learn how you can build and test your application on GitHub&amp;rsquo;s CI, and get your Kotlin/JS web apps published for free.
In this post, we are going to configure GitHub Actions and Pages so that new code pushed to our repository or added via pull request is automatically validated (by having the project built and our tests run on GitHub&amp;rsquo;s servers), and code pushed to the main branch of our project is automatically made available to the public (by generating and publishing production artifacts of our app).</description></item></channel></rss>